בוקר טוב Boker tov today's דף daf officially is י"ד yud daled
14 we're a little bit behind so we're gonna really try to
pick up the pace we start at the bottom of י"ג עמוד
ד' yud gimmel amud daled and we pick up with and we're
in the middle of a discussion of the statement of the difference
between תשעה באב Tisha B'Av and אבילות avelus in which even cold
water is not allowed as for bathing as opposed to תענית ta'anis
where it's only hot water and both of those statements are theoretically
up for debate maybe אבילות avelus is only hot water or maybe
תענית ta'anis is even cold water anyway that's the issue although we
ended with a very powerful proof of a of a
that the problem of going to the מקוה mikvah on תשעה באב
Tisha B'Av which everybody seems to assume which seems to clearly indicate
that on תשעה באב Tisha B'Av cold water is forbidden although the
גמרא Gemara gets out of it okay now the גמרא Gemara continues
תא שמע ta shema תשעה באב Tisha B'Av thank you so much
it's the asterisk it's about 20 lines from the bottom asterisk at
the beginning of the
line כשאמרו keshe'amru אסור assur במלאכה bemlacha לא אמרו lo amru אלא
ela ביום bayom so when they said on the fast days that
it's forbidden to do work on the once that become the תעניות
ta'aniyot for גשמים geshamim once they become the more serious full-blown versions
you can't do work they only said it in the in the
daytime and that we've already discussed before right where the גמרא Gemara
said you know מה אסיפת זקנים ma assifat zkenim is ביום bayom
so the whole idea of not doing מלאכה melacha and gathering people
together is about the day so כשאמרו keshe'amru אסור assur במלאכה bemlacha
לא אמרו lo amru אלא ela ביום bayom אבל aval בלילה balaila
מותר mutar in the night before it's
permissible okay וכשאמרו u'keshe'amru אסור assur בנעילת הסנדל bine'ilat hasandal when they
said you can't wear a shoe לא אמרו lo amru אלא ela
בעיר ba'ir only in the city אבל aval בדרך baderech מותר mutar
on the way it's permissible if you're traveling the simplest explanation for
that is that you know you have to just adjust to realities
you know if you have to travel it's impossible it's over demanding
to ask somebody not to wear a shoe but the other thing
that I do want to also sort of alert us to again
is the public nature and the communal nature of some of these
practices closing the bathhouses closing the stores etc so not wearing shoes
although it is very private as well you know even an individual
observing אבילות avelut doesn't wear shoes but again to emphasize that being
done in the city not when you're sort of out on travel
there's also a you know an aspect of the sort of of
the public private aspect there as well but okay so that's allowed
and now we get to the point where we're quoting all of
this
הכיצד ha keitzad how is this possible I'm sorry יוצא לדרך yotzei
laderech נועל no'el נכנס לעיר nichnas la'ir חולץ choleitz when you start
when you go out to leave you can put on your shoe
when you come as soon as you come into the city you
have to take it off fine וכשאמרו u'keshe'amru אסור assur ברחיצה birchitzah
and when they said you cannot bathe לא אמרו lo amru אלא
ela כל גופו kol gufo they only said your entire body אבל
aval פניו ידיו ורגליו panav yadav v'raglav מותר mutar but you can
do your hands and face and legs again that's a minimal amount
that is needed just you know for general well-being okay וכן אתה
מוצא vechen ata motzei במנודה bimnudeh ובאבל u'be'avel and the same laws
that apply here the allowance of going of wearing the shoes outside
of the city the allowance presumably of washing hands feet and face
that's also and the same prohibitions but the same allowances are true
also by somebody in חרם cherem מנודה mnudeh which we're not going
to discuss and somebody in אבילות avelut now I did say you
might notice that I intentionally left off מלאכה melacha because it is
not true that an אבל avel is allowed to do מלאכה melacha
at night and not in the day I mean and so you
know so and here in the cases here the מלאכה melacha is
about as we've seen gathering the people and so on also city-wide
you know or community-wide you might need to just allow a certain
amount of מלאכה melacha to get done
but at the individual level it's not true the איסור מלאכה issur
melacha applies day and night so anyway presumably though focusing on the
last two that the prohibitions and the allowances are the same by
the אבל avel and the מנודה mnudeh as they are by the
person in תענית ta'anit one thing I will say about the מנודה
mnudeh and the אבל avel and putting them in the same category
is that it echoes the line from our משנה mishna that when
even all of the fasts pass it says they start being
נוהג noheig מנהגי אבילות minhagei avelut it didn't use the word אבילות
avelut but it said you know it said what did it
say ממעטין במשא ומתן בבניין ובנטיעה כבני אדם הנזופים למקום mema'atin bemasa
u'matan bevinyan u'veneti'ah kevnei adam hanezofim lamakom people that are basically being
rejected by God and that idea of מנודה mnudeh is essentially the
worldly status of what that means of being נזופים למקום nezofim lamakom
right so God rejects you and you are basically מנודה mnudeh from
God so the community is sort of rejecting you and you are
a מנודה mnudeh from the community so what is again worth noticing
is that this aspect of נזופים nezofim is the halachic counterpart of
נזופים nezofim מנודה mnudeh and for a lot for a lot of
הלכות halachot the status the practices of נידוי niduy that the individual
adopts for himself not just for the community is relevant. parallel to
the practices of אבילות. aveilut. And again, one can see it about
A, mourning that sense of loss, and of B, being and owning
that sense of, you know, tragedy, the tragedy of a loss of
a immediate relative, but the tragedy of being distant from the community,
distant from God, rejected. And also as we've discussed, some of the
practices of אבילות aveilut themselves are expressive of the idea that you
are not engaged in the community. You're not taking care of your
basically bodily needs, you're not going to work, you're just completely you
can't integrate into the community at this stage, and it's similar here,
you know, practices of the מנודה. menudeh. So again, I just will
mention the once again, the juxtaposition of those two echoing the ניזופים
למקום nizufim lamakom in our משנה. mishnah. Okay, so now why is
this relevant to our question of cold water, hot water, etc.? Because
let's take a look. מאי לאו אכולהו? mai lav akuleihu? When it
says that these laws and allowances are the same for מנודה menudeh
and אבל, aveil, presumably it's referring to everything, both the shoes and
the bathing. ובמאי עסקינן? uvmai askinan? And when we're talking about the
bathing, what are we talking about? אילימא בחמים? eileima bechamim? If we're
talking about hot water, so פניו ידיו ורגליו מי שרו? panav yadav
veraglav mi sharu? It would be impossible to say that the allowance
of face and hands and feet applies is allowed for hot water.
Why? דאמר רב ששת אבל אסור להושיט אצבעו בחמים? de’amar rav sheshet
aveil assur lehoshit etzba’o bechamim? That it's he says, and as presumably
we're assuming that רב ששת rav sheshet is consistent with this, that
an אבל aveil can't even stick his little pinky into the water,
or his little finger. So certainly I mean the whole hand obviously
not in hot water, excuse me. So if there's an allowance for
hands, face, and feet for water, to be consistent with רב ששת,
rav sheshet, it has to be cold water. Okay. אלא לאו בצונן?
ela lav betzonen? So what it must be saying is cold water
is generally forbidden, but it's allowed for hands, face, and feet. Okay.
And now what does that prove? So if basically it's saying that
cold water is forbidden, so it's talking about the תענית. ta’anit. Right?
So again, since it here says the same law we're saying by
תענית ta’anit applies to אבל aveil and we're allowing hands, face, and
feet, and therefore the assumption is that can't be allowed by אבל,
aveil, it has to be talking about cold—unless if it's hot water,
it must be cold water. So if it's talking about cold water,
now it's saying that cold water is אסור assur not just for
the אבל, aveil, but because this ברייתא braita is comparing אבל aveil
to תענית, ta’anit, it's saying that cold water is אסור assur even
in the case of תענית, ta’anit, bathing in cold water. So that
goes against the argument that in תענית ta’anit it's only hot water.
So the גמרא gemara says it's pretty good proof, right? It basically
equates the bathing issues for תענית ta’anit and אבילות aveilut and we're
trying to distinguish them. So the גמרא gemara
says לא לעולם בחמים. lo le’olam bechamim. We're only talking about hot
water, and only on תענית ta’anit only hot water is forbidden, and
hot water is on the whole body, but hot water is even
allowed on face, hands, and feet for a תענית. ta’anit. תענית ta’anit
is different than אבל. aveil. So what do you do with the
phrase that equates אבל? aveil? ודקא קשיא לך וכן אתה מוצא במנודה
ובאבל? vedeka kashya lach vechen atah motze bemenudeh ube’aveil?
That line of that a person in נידוי niduy and אבל aveil
have the same הלכות halakhot and here we're distinguishing them on the
plane of bathing. אשארא קאי. ashe’ara ka’ei. It's talking about the rest.
Okay, it's not talking—the comparison was only was not, although it's funny,
the immediate thing that was that it preceded it was a discussion
of bathing. We're saying that they're not really being compared about the
bathing issue, they're being compared about the rest. The problem is the
rest is the מלאכה melacha and the shoes. But so the shoes
we can compare them, you can wear the shoes out of the
city, but the מלאכה melacha as we already said, the allowance of
night doesn't apply to an אבל. aveil. So it's not really the
rest, it's only comparing them to the one in the middle, not
the first one, not the last one. It's very strange. רש"י ותוספות
Rashi veTosafot try to try to somehow deal with it and say
we're also talking about anointing, but anointing wasn't mentioned in the ברייתא.
braita. It's a difficult answer. The simple sense of this ברייתא braita
is that אבילות aveilut and and what do you call it, and
תענית ta’anit are the same. So if you think about what the
most obvious evidence we'd had is we'd had the ברייתא braita yesterday
that going to the מקווה mikvah is a problem on on what
do you call it, on תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, which seems to
be a very good evidence that cold water is forbidden when it's
related to אבל, aveil, אבילות. aveilut. We've had this ברייתא braita which
seems to equate completely, you know, אבילות aveilut in the matter of
bathing, אבילות aveilut to תענית, ta’anit, and presumably based on the statement
of of hot water for the even on the finger for an
אבל, aveil, again seems to be saying for cold water. So the
simple sense, if you combine the evidence, is cold water is אסור
assur whether for תענית, ta’anit, whether for אבל, aveil, whether for תענית.
ta’anit. But the גמרא gemara is managing to maneuver around it and
still try to leave its options open. Okay, and the still the
position on the table that has been articulated is cold water for
תענית—hot ta’anit water is only is forbidden for תענית, ta’anit, even cold
water for אבל. aveil. Let's keep on going. תא שמע, ta shema,
come and hear. דאמר רבי אבא הכהן משום רבי יוסי הכהן, de’amar
Rabi Abba HaKohen mishum Rabi Yosi HaKohen, so רבי אבא הכהן Rabi
Abba HaKohen said in the name of רבי יוסי הכהן, Rabi Yosi
HaKohen, מעשה ומתו בניו של רבי יוסי בן רבי חנינא. ma’aseh umetu
banav shel Rabi Yosi ben Rabi Chanina. children of רבי יוסי בן
רבי חנינא Rabi Yossi ben Rabi Chanina all died, נעבעך, nebach, it
probably was some type of a disease or
some type of a plague. ורחץ בצונן כל שבעה. verachatz betzonen kol
shiva. And even though he observed אבלות, avelut, presumably he was observing
many אבלויות aveluyot because they died sequentially as we'll see, so he
bathed himself with cold water. So you see you can bathe cold
water by אבל. avel. You see cold water is permissible for an
אבל. avel. גמרא Gemara says no, that whole thing was an exception.
התם כשתכפוהו אבליו הוי. hatam keshetakfuhu avalav havay. That was a case
where the mournings sort of piled up on him one after the
other. דתניא, detanya, we taught a ברייתא, braita, תכפוהו אבליו זה אחר
זה, takfuhu avalav zeh achar zeh, חס ושלום chas veshalom somebody has
various אבלויות aveluyot that pile up one after the other, relatives die
in quick succession חס ושלום. chas veshalom. So what? So there are
certain allowances. הכביד שיער שערו, hikvid sear saaro, he
and his hair got heavy, so now this person hasn't taken a
haircut for weeks and weeks. אז מיקל בתער. az meikel betaar. He
can lighten his hair with a razor, meaning not get a real
haircut with scissors, but he can lighten it a little bit, cut
some of the hair. ומכבס כסותו במים. umechabbes kesuto bemayim. And his
clothes are now filthy and stinky. So fine, we'll allow him to
launder his clothes a little bit. אמר רב חסדא בתער אבל לא
במספריים. Amar Rav Chisda: Betaar aval lo bemisparayim. And this is precise.
You can use a razor but not scissors. במים בלא נתר. Bemayim
belo neter. You can use water but you can't use soap. ובלא
חול uvelo chol or sand other types of cleansing agents. Okay, so
therefore similar to those allowances, we would let somebody bathe in cold
water, but the general rule would be
that you cannot bathe, an אבל avel cannot bathe in cold water.
If anything, it seems to actually prove the point that an אבל
avel can't bathe in cold water because the whole point of it
seemed to be to emphasize that that was an exception. Okay, so
therefore again consistent with the idea that an אבל avel cannot bathe
in cold water, that seems to be very consistent. אמר רבא. Amar
Rava. So that's the argument, אבל avel אסור assur in cold, תענית
taanit only hot. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. Now says רבא Rava a
different position. That was רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, what we've been dealing
with was רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. Now we have רבא. Rava. אבל
מותר לרחוץ בצונן כל שבעה. Avel mutar lirchotz betzonen kol shiva. An
אבל avel can bathe in cold water all seven days. Against presumably
the evidence we had before about going to the מקוה, mikveh, which
seemed to say it was אסור, assur, this recent thing which seemed
to say bathing in cold water was an exception for the guy
who had multiple אבלויות. aveluyot. He says no, that's the rule, an
אבל avel can use cold water. מידי דהוי אבשרא וחמרא. midi dehavay
abisra vechamra. The same thing that we find by meat and wine.
What does that mean? It means that we don't have this idea
that an אבל avel is supposed to be in pain. Right? That
was the question we raised. Why should an אבל avel be more
חמור chamur than תענית ציבור? taanit tzibur? So what רש"י Rashi said
before was, well an אבל avel really feels the pain much more,
like צער דגופיה. tzaar degufay. Like it's very personal. And somehow an
idea of אבלות avelut is to express that thing of sense of
pain and suffering over the loss by these acts of self-denial,
non-indulgence, even more than just non-indulgence, real like afflicting of pain, non-indulgence
would be hot water, here it's even cold water. That's what we
said before. רבא Rava is coming to counteract that. רבא Rava is
saying since when do you get the idea that אבלות avelut is
about suffering,
physical self-denial and about pain? You allowed somebody to have meat and
wine, so it's not about the like physical pleasures of the body
that are the issue. There's other... it's... אבלות avelut is about something
else. Like we said, might be expressing this idea about being just
so, complete focusing somebody on the אבלות, avelut, completely taking away all
the outside distractions, feeling oneself as outside of society,
as completely like not able to attend to one's bodily needs, but
that's very different than the devaluing of the sense of an expression
of expressing physical pain. Okay, so that's an interesting question. What are
we trying to communicate through these different practices? And he says it's
not צער. tzaar. And therefore, there's the only issue is hot water.
You don't go, maybe you don't want to indulge in pleasures, although
about meat and wine could be indulge, but anyway, but it's certainly
not about צער. tzaar. Fascinating. So now, okay, now we have to
see, now about proving or disproving this? Because the evidence was that
cold water was אסור. assur. So מיתיבי, meitivei, says the גמרא, Gemara,
I'll ask you on this.
אין הבוגרת רשאה לנבל עצמה בימי אבל אביה, Ein habogeret resha'ah lenabbel
atzmah bimei avel aviha, top of י"ג עמוד ב', yod gimmel amud
bet, אין הבוגרת רשאה לנבל עצמה בימי אבל אביה. Ein habogeret resha'ah
lenabbel atzmah bimei avel aviha. A young woman
who's of mature age, I mean or like marriageable age, so this
is a woman
and still unmarried. So בוגרת bogeret is a woman who's at the
old age of twelve and a half, נעבעך, nebach, and still hasn't
married. That's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. Since this one has
to really be focusing on getting her a חתן, chatan, she's already
twelve and a half.
So she or older, she, I could obviously be older but it
starts at twelve and a half. Anyway, so she now נעבעך nebach
is sitting שבעה shiva for her father. If she has too much,
a lot of people hopefully are going to be coming to the
house to pay שבעה shiva calls. If she looks too disheveled, then
she's going to be hurting her marriage her marriage prospects. So she
cannot overly... Wait, the משנה Mishna says up to 12. If she
is over 12, then I guess she could obviously be older, but
it starts at 12 and anyway, so she's now נעבעך nebach sitting
שבעה shiva for her father.
If she has too much, a lot of people hopefully going to
be coming to the house to pay שבעה shiva calls, if she
looks too disheveled, then she's going to be hurting her marriage, her
marriage prospects. So she cannot overly disfigure herself, not disfigure but anyway,
become dishevel. Dishevel herself I guess, I don't know anyway, it's more
also, it's more than disheveled but less than disfigure. Anyway, make herself
disgusting בימי אבל אביה biymei avel aviha when she's sitting שבעה. shiva.
Okay, הנערה רשאית, hanara reshayit, but if she's not yet of marriageable
age, she's only a נערה, na'ara, she's only 12, not 12 and
a half, because under 12 she wouldn't be חייבא באבלות. chayeva b'aveilus.
So he would be permiss- not permissible, she'd be obligated, meaning it
sounds like there's a special allowance we're making for a בוגרת. bogeret.
So how does this all work out? מאי לאו ברחיצה? mai lav
birkhitza? Now we must be talking about the question about the permissibility
of bathing. So ובמאי? uvamai? Now what type of bathing? אילימא בחמין,
ileima b'chamin, if we're talking about using hot water, אינה בוגרת רשאית,
eina bogeret reshayit, so a בוגרת bogeret cannot deny herself taking care
of these bathing needs? ואמר רב חסדא אבל אסור להושיט אצבעו בחמין,
v'amar Rav Chisda avel assur l'hoshit etzba'o b'chamin, an אבל avel can't
even stick a finger into hot water, which again, maybe you could
say, well that's the exception here, but given the extreme nature of
that statement, the גמרא Gemara is not willing to think that we
would make an exception for the בוגרת. bogeret. So it can't be
we're allowing this, the בוגרת, bogeret, this, you know, this more mature
young woman, to actually use hot water. That's not possible. אלא לאו
בצונן, ela lav b'tzonen, it must be we're allowing cold water. And
what we're saying is we'll allow her to take a cold bath,
we won't allow, you know, the נערה, na'ara, younger woman. Cold water
is what's אסור, assur, but that we'll allow for her. But hot
water is like off the table. So even though they're both אסור,
assur, there's obviously hot water seen as much more severe. So the
גמרא Gemara brings it as a seeming proof that cold water is
אסור assur and a proof against רבא. Rava. So the גמרא Gemara
says, again it could've brought all the proofs from yesterday, particularly the
idea that there was a problem going to the מקוה mikveh on
תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, which certainly seems to indicate cold water is
a problem. But okay, the גמרא Gemara is bringing this to show
that cold water is a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says לא,
lo, אכיח ופריח, achich uprich,
it's not talking about water at all, it's talking about makeup, it's
talking about eye shadow and rouge and whatever these things are. And
you know, put on a little makeup, that's what it's talking about.
Okay, and maybe it's not even that makeup is אסור. assur. Whoever
heard that makeup was אסור? assur? I mean we'll get to it.
בפני איש. bifnei ish. So maybe it just means it you know,
you know, therefore maybe it's really even saying it's basically not אסור.
assur. Practice people maybe don't do it, and or you know, but
a בוגרת bogeret can't, you know, overly indulge in her אבלות aveilus
to not do it. She should be, you know, she she needs
to do it. Again, we will sort of bracket the whole idea
here of the focus on this girl at the time of her
שבעה shiva as a concern about marriage prospects. But okay, we'll have
to just accept some of the societal realities in which the גמרא
Gemara was functioning. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says לימא מסייע ליה. leima
mesayei lei. What?
Her father was died. I mean, she doesn't have anyone who would
take care of her.
Oh, that's an interesting point. Oh, that's a nice point. Meaning maybe
the גמרא Gemara has a heightened focus on this because otherwise the
father would be the one that generally would arrange for these things.
Oh, I like that. Thank you. That that makes it a little
bit more understandable, like why there's such a focus right now on
this issue. But you're right, the father is dead, so it does
heighten that aspect. Okay. לימא מסייע ליה. leima mesayei lei. Let's try
again to, let's try now to prove רבא Rava before we try
to contradict רבא, Rava, now let's try to prove רבא Rava that
cold water is permissible. ואמר רבי אבא הכהן משום רבי יוסי הכהן,
v'amar Rabi Abba HaKohen mishum Rabi Yosei HaKohen, exactly what we brought
before as a question, now we're going to try to support. מעשה
שמתו בניו של רבי יוסי בר חנינא ורחץ בצונן כל שבעה. ma'aseh
shemetu banav shel Rabi Yosei bar Chanina v'rachatz b'tzonen kol shiva. So
you see, here we have a story of somebody bathing in cold
water. So he says no, as we said before, התם בתכופו אבליו
זה אחר זה. hatam bitkhufo avalav zeh achar zeh. That was an
exception because there were multiple, you know, deaths right after another. דתניא
תכופו אבליו זה אחר זה, detanya tkhufo avalav zeh achar zeh, if
various mourning practices, you know, mourning fell one after another, הכביד שערו
מיקל בתער ומכבס כסותו במים, hichvid se'aro meikel b'ta'ar umkhabes k'suto b'mayim,
lighten the hair with a razor, bathe the clothes in water. אמר
רב חסדא בתער ולא במספרים, amar Rav Chisda b'ta'ar v'lo b'misparayim, razor,
not scissors. במים ולא בנתר ולא בחול, b'mayim v'lo b'neter v'lo b'chol,
water and not various cleansing agents. לא באו. lo ba'u. Okay.
So that's what anyways, what before was a proof is now, what
before was a question is now a proof. Again, it ignores the
most obvious proof against רבא, Rava, which was the case of going
to the מקוה. mikveh. So now we have the debate. It seems
like we settled on the idea that תענית ציבור ta'anit tzibur is
only hot water, not cold. And now we have a debate, I'm
sorry, only hot water is forbidden on a תענית ציבור, ta'anit tzibur,
cold water is permissible. And we have a debate what the story
is by an אבל. avel. Okay, אמר רבא, amar Rava, אבל אסור
בצונן כל שבעה. avel assur b'tzonen kol shiva. So, I'm sorry, before
I was saying רבא, Rava, but it wasn't רבא. Rava. Who was
saying the previous one that was saying it was מותר? mutar? No,
that was רבא. Rava. That was אמר רבא. amar Rava. Okay. So
איכא דאמרי. ika d'amri. I forgot the two key words איכא דאמרי.
ika d'amri. Sorry. איכא דאמרי אמר רבא. ika d'amri amar Rava. So
now we're having רבא Rava saying that cold water is allowed and
in contrast to רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. But there's another version of
רבא, Rava, which is the same as רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. Others
say that רבא Rava said אבל אסור בצונן כל שבעה, avel assur
b'tzonen kol shiva, אבל avel is forbidden in cold water, just like
רב חסדא Rav Chisda said. מאי שנא מבשר ויין? mai shena mibasar
v'yayin? Now how is it different from wine and meat? How's it
different from meat and wine? Because according to the first version, that
was a really good argument that it's not about צער. tza'ar. So
why here, what is the logic to say why cold water is
forbidden? So the גמרא Gemara says the following: How's it different than
wine meat and wine? So התם לצכוכי פחדיה הוא דעביד. hasam letachuchei
pachtei hu de'avid. There he's doing it to like abate his fear,
to relieve his anxiety. Meaning, similar to the idea we said that
we've already seen some exceptions, you know, about sometimes we'll allow you
to, what do you call it, to you know, like if a
lot of אבילות aveilus we'll allow certain exceptions, if you have to
go outside the city, we'll allow the person to put on shoes.
You know, there are various exceptions. We even raised the question yesterday,
why not sit in a תענית? tayniss? Maybe because that's unreasonable to
suggest. So within these things, the practices, there's certain exceptions. So the
גמרא Gemara here is saying an important idea. It's saying, you know
what, in theory, an אבל avel should be אסור assur בשר ויין.
basar veyayin. Really, it should be. That you know, the same way
an אונן, onein, I mean, by the way, it's not like we
don't have this idea as a practice. An אונן onein is forbidden
in בשר ויין. basar veyayin. So logically an אבל avel should be.
The only thing is is that, you know, we need to give
him, allow him to to do that. Maybe specifically it's interesting what
exactly aspect of that? Is it the wine? You know, because you
know, some people, you know, that's the you know, again you
have to be careful it doesn't slide into alcoholism, but some people
drink a little bit, you know, as a way of dealing with
stress. So that could explain the wine aspect. I'm not exactly sure
how that has to do with eating the red meat. Again, maybe
I don't know, maybe somehow a little moment to indulge in a
little pleasure is a little way of dealing with when it gets
too overwhelming.
So the גמרא Gemara actually sees here that you know what, maybe
there is an idea of צער, tza'ar, but we have to give
you certain allowances. So בשר ויין basar veyayin we'll allow, but it
doesn't mean that we're going to allow the cold water, and there
really is this idea of physical צער tza'ar during אבילות. aveilus. I
should say, but there's a fascinating debate in the ראשונים Rishonim whether
to see אנינות oninus and אבילות aveilus as essentially the same practice
or to see them as fundamentally different. Obviously, they are fundamentally different.
אנינות oninus is אסור assur in בשר ויין, basar veyayin, you don't
do מצוות, mitzvos, but you don't have any of the מנהגי אבילות.
minhagei aveilus. And אבילות aveilus is almost like everything the opposite. But
some want to sort of see that the difference is really a
more expression of which exceptions apply at which places. Like by אנינות
oninus it's obviously you don't do certain מצוות mitzvos because you're a
person is involved in burial. But the איסור issur בשר ויין basar
veyayin fundamentally does apply to an אבל. avel. It's just by an
אבל avel we make an exception and we don't make an exception
by the אונן. onein. Other practices, like, you know, not putting on
shoes and not bathing, whatever, maybe should apply to an אונן, onein,
but we don't want to—but we make an exception there because we've
got to allow the person to focus, you know, to do the
work needed to take care of the burial. So there's an interesting
way of seeing it like it's all really the same but with
different exceptions. I only mention it here because of the בשר ויין
basar veyayin that is taken—that we know about that idea by אנינות
oninus and the גמרא Gemara is saying here that in principle it
applies to an אבל avel except that we have to allow for
an exception. Okay.
Yes? Thinking about the issue of צער. tza'ar. You were so convincing
before that it doesn't make sense to add צער tza'ar onto צער.
tza'ar. Right. So how do you know over here that they're talking
about
צער?
tza'ar? Well because the—well the—you mean maybe the—because if the reason of
not doing the cold water was not related to צער tza'ar and
was related to something else, then it should have used that as
the reason to differentiate it from why we allow בשר ויין. basar
veyayin. It should have said בשר ויין basar veyayin you're right, that
proves that it's not about צער, tza'ar, but here's the reason why
even so the אבל avel can't bathe in cold water. Forget צער,
tza'ar, some other reason. It didn't say that. It accepted the premise
of the argument. Right? The premise of the argument was that בשר
ויין basar veyayin is about צער tza'ar or not having it, and
cold—not having cold water is about
צער. tza'ar. And fundamentally if one is אסור, assur, the other is
אסור. assur. I accept the premise of the argument, and therefore you're
right. בשר ויין basar veyayin should be אסור, assur, but I'll tell
you why it's not. It's a special exception that we need to
allow, you know, the אבל avel to deal with his anxiety.
So wait, where's where's? Oh.
Have you introduced—Where is that? No. I you're right. I've introduced it.
The גמרא Gemara though, you have to otherwise come up with a
reason why the גמרא Gemara thinks that בשר ויין basar veyayin is
a relevant argument to the idea of cold water. That the—the גמרא's
Gemara assuming if בשר ויין basar veyayin is אסור, assur, cold water
should be. If cold water is אסור, assur, then בשר ויין basar
veyayin should be אסור. assur. And the גמרא Gemara in both places
accepts the premise of the argument. So you have to figure out
some reason for that logic. And it seems to be that, you
know, to me that's what the argument seems to be.
And might it be that
בשר ויין basar veyayin are luxuries, but cold water is not a
luxury?
Right. So that would have been the perfect—that would have been the
perfect answer. The גמרא Gemara could have said בשר ויין—no. basar veyayin
No, but that would lead to the reverse. Meaning, you're right, but
if בשר ויין basar veyayin is מותר, mutar, then it shows even
תענוג ta'anug is allowed. Right? So it would even heighten the question
of why are you making
cold water
forbidden? Right, that was the גמרא's Gemara initial argument. If בשר ויין
basar v'yayin is מותר, mutar, then... if... alright, if... it's okay, but
I think we're saying the same thing. בשר ויין basar v'yayin is
a luxury and an indulgence. Hot water probably is in that same
category or somewhere in that continuum. Not even doing cold water is
even... is even more, is even צער, tza'ar, is even on the,
you know, further at the edge. So they're all on a continuum,
and the גמרא's Gemara trying to argue one from the other, which
shows that that's the issue at stake, seeing it in that way.
Alright, well, we'll unpack that more later, but it seems clear that
that's the argument, and the גמרא Gemara accepts the premise of the
argument and just makes בשר ויין basar v'yayin an exception. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now we're just going to
go through the same proofs again. לימא מסייע ליה, leima m'sayei lei,
let me come try to prove it. אינה בוגרת שלא נטלה עצמה,
eina bogeret shelo natla atzma, so בוגרת bogeret can not again dishevel
herself. הנערה בשעה, ha na'ara b'sha'ah, the נערה na'ara is allowed or
is obligated. במאי? b'mai? אילימא בחמים, i'leima b'chamim, if we're talking about
the use or non-use of hot water, אינה בוגרת שלא? eina bogeret
shelo? ואמר רב חסדא אבל אסור להושיט פניו בחמים, v'amar Rav Chisda
aval asur lehachit panyv b'chamim, we never would have allowed the בוגרת
bogeret to use hot water. אלא בצונן. ela b'tzonen. Must be cold
water. And it's a special exception by a בוגרת, bogeret, and but
the general rule is that cold water is forbidden. גמרא Gemara says,
לא בכחול ופרכוס, lo b'kichul u'firchus, maybe we're talking about makeup. Okay.
So we haven't proved it. And again ignoring the great proof from
going to the מקוה. mikveh. So where are we about all of
this? We are basically at the conclusion that by a תענית ta'anit
it's only hot water, which is an indulgence, right? If anything, by
תענית ta'anit you're denying yourself food. You would say there again, going
back to the point we were just discussing, the logical parallel to
denying yourself food is denying yourself even cold water for bathing, right?
It's not just, but okay, but maybe denying food is already enough
and then the only things we're going to add are indulgences. It's
not exactly clear. But anyway, A, it's interesting that a תענית ta'anit
is only hot water. Okay, that's point number one. And point number
two is אבלות avelut is even cold water. Now why is אבלות
avelut even cold water? Right? One way of expressing this is צער
tza'ar and a heightened degree of צער tza'ar and that seems to
be the focus of the גמרא Gemara and then you have to
explain the meat and wine why it's allowed and you make that
an exception as a way of dealing with the, you know, the
anxiety and with the overwhelming emotions. Okay, but fundamentally there is an
idea of צער tza'ar or you could, against what seems to be
the assumption of the גמרא, Gemara, argue that it has nothing to
do with צער, tza'ar, it's working on a completely separate plane and
has to do as I said with more being just out, you
know, completely focused on the אבלות avelut outside of the normal, you
know, sort of lived life within society. But anyway, but it does
seem that the evidence, however you explain it, or the גמרא Gemara
is settling on the idea that cold water is אסור assur for
an אבל avel and only hot water for a תענית. ta'anit. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
where were we? אמר רב חסדא... Amar Rav Chisda... אמר רב חסדא
זאת אומרת, Amar Rav Chisda zot omeret, since we're making an issue
of this כחול ופרכוס kichul u'firchus by an אבל, avel, a normal
one except for the exception of a בוגרת, bogeret, this tells you...
אבל אסור בתכבוסת כל שבעה, avel asur b'tichboset kol shiva, that if
you can't actually do makeup, you can't actually you can't do laundry
either. Now that's a very bizarre זאת אומרת. zot omeret. Like laundry
seems to be the fundamental איסור. issur. כחול ופרכוס kichul u'firchus we
never heard of, you know it's fundamental because the earlier discussion that
mentioned exceptions about laundry and using water and not using soap and
detergents by a person that had multiple ones. Okay, so it's very
bizarre what exactly is going on here. So...
כחול
ופרכוס
kichul
u'firchus is also makeup?
Yeah, yeah.
What? Yeah.
It says it's dying from a Greek word possibly.
Okay.
Yeah, and so רבי עקיבא איגר Rabbi Akiva Eiger in the גליון
הש"ס... Gilyon Hashas... רבי עקיבא איגר Rabbi Akiva Eiger in the גליון
הש"ס, Gilyon Hashas, if people have it on the far left, asks
the question, and if you look like the second half of it
he says, גם למאי צריך להוכחה מאוקמתא זו הנישמע מברייתא דלעיל דהצבא
אבל מכבס כסותו במים ומוכח מזה דאבל אסור בכיבוס דצריך עיון גדול.
Gam lemai tzarich l'hochacha mi'ukmeta zu hanishma mibraita d'le'eil de'hatzeva avel mechabbes
ksuto b'mayim u'mucha mizzeh de'avel asur b'kibbus de'tzarich iyun gadol. So that's
a real problem what type of thing. Now maybe the זאת אומרת
zot omeret was going on something else, but it sounds like it
was going on the כחול ופרכוס kichul u'firchus which seems like a
very bizarre that he would need to have that derivation. Okay.
It could mean that she can't wear clothes that had been laundered?
I... that's not the language of תכבוסת. tichboset. I mean, you're right,
it would fit better, but okay. והלכתא. v'hilcheta. Now the הלכה halakha
is... so that זאת אומרת zot omeret seems a lot a little
out of place, but anyway, back to the point.
והלכתא v'hilcheta אבל... avel... So we are concluding as where the whole
thrust of the גמרא Gemara had been going, that by an אבל
Avel even cold water is forbidden, but we will have an allowance
like we had an allowance before for hands, face, and feet. We'll
have that allowance for an אבל, Avel, but only for the cold
water, because again, going to this idea that even the pinky in
hot water is forbidden, but we will have that allowance for cold
water. Okay, but by a תענית, Taanis, presumably, it's only hot water
is forbidden, with a similar allowance of hands, face, and feet, but
there for hot water.
Okay.
אבל לסוך, Avel l'sooch, to anoint oneself, so put oil on one's
body, אפילו כל שהוא אסור, afilu kol shehu assur, even a little
bit. That's more like the hot water. That's more like an indulgence,
although it wasn't as much of an indulgence then, but anyway. But
therefore, there would be no allowance for the סיכה, sichah, and it's
sort of, it's like the hot water. ואם להעביר את הזוהמא, V'im
l'haavir es hazuhama, but however, and this is a major reason that
people did anoint themselves, is because they stank. And so if you
are doing it, you know, depending on your bathing practices, and so
if you are doing it in order to abate the stench, מותר,
mutar, then it is permissible. Okay, and similarly by תשעה באב, Tishah
B'Av, we have allowances, you know, about using hot water, you know,
or using water if you need to get really clean something as
opposed to just doing it, you know, when it's just for the
sake of bathing itself, but if it's really to directly remove some
dirt or something, then there are allowances. Okay. So that is the
end of that fascinating discussion, which on the one hand, we had
a momentary combination of a comparison of אבלות Avelus to מנודה, menudeh,
which gets us back to the משנה, Mishnah, and on the other
hand, we also have the, what do you call it, the distinction
of אבלות Avelus from תענית, Taanis, which makes sense, but raises again
the question, is to what degree are the practices of אבלות Avelus
about צער, tza'ar, or are they about, and maybe even heightened צער
tza'ar and therefore more severe practices, or are they really about functioning
on a different plane, which could also explain some of the practices.
Okay. Now back to some issues we've been talking about before. It's
funny the way the גמרא Gemara like shifts without even signaling it
back to another topic. But anyway, okay, the גמרא Gemara says like
this: צלותא דתעניתא היכי מדכרינן. Tzlusa d'taanisa heichi madkrinan.
Where do we mention, we were talking before a little bit implicitly
about whether somebody is considered a תענית, Taanis, if it's תענית שעות,
taanis sha'os, etc., other types of things. Implicitly there's an issue about
saying the special תפילות tefillos of the תענית, Taanis, the עננו. Aneinu.
Where do you say it in the שמנה עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei? Okay,
that's a good question. So אמר ליה רב יהודה לרב יצחק בריה.
Amar leh Rav Yehuda l'Rav Yitzchak breh. Rav Yehuda said to Rav
Yitzchak his son, ודרש, v'darash, and he expounded: יחיד שקיבל עליו תענית,
Yachid shekibel alav taanis,
again, interestingly re-echoing those earlier discussions of the individual, although now we've
been totally in the ציבור tzibur context. An individual who accepted a
תענית, Taanis, מתפלל של תענית, mispallel shel taanis, has to pray the,
even if it's an individual, even if it's not a תענית ציבור,
taanis tzibur, you still say the special תפילה, tefillah, you say the
עננו. Aneinu. והיכן אומרה? V'heichan omrah?
Where do you say it? בין גואל לרופא. Bein Goel l'Rofei.
You say the עננו, Aneinu, which we have as our practice that
the שליח ציבור shliach tzibur says it at מנחה, Mincha, says it
in a special עננו Aneinu as a standalone ברכה bracha between גואל
Goel and רופא, Rofei, right? Everybody knows that what we say on
a, you know, one of the historical fast days, right?
So here it's an added independent blessing.
אחרי רפאנו, Acharei Refaeinu, right here it says, oh, I'm sorry, not
מנחה, Mincha, מנחה Mincha is the יחיד, yachid, excuse me. That's the
יחיד. yachid. The שליח ציבור shliach tzibur says it already at שחרית,
Shacharis, right? עננו ה' עננו ביום צום תעניתנו כי בצרה גדולה אנחנו
אל תפן אל רשענו ואל תתעלם Aneinu Hashem aneinu b'yom tzom taaniseinu
ki b'tzara gedola anachnu al tefen el risheinu v'al titalem etc. ברוך
אתה ה' העונה בעת צרה. Baruch Atah Hashem haoneh b'eis tzara. Now
the interesting question to ask is, why does it belong between גואל
Goel and רופא? Rofei? What's it doing there? Right? Now so and
one thing I think I'd like to point out is is that
the ברכות, brachot, end, there's a shift, I don't know if people
are aware, between the ברכות brachot in the שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei
between those, although everything is the לשון רבים, lashon rabim, there's a
shift between those that are much more about personal needs and those
that are about national needs. So you know, you have, you have
דעת, Da'as, סליחה, slichah, גאולה, geulah, but the גאולה geulah of גואל
Goel is much more about like personal redemption, save me from my
travails. Okay, רפואה. refuah. Okay, then you have ברכת השנים, birkas hashanim,
right? Which is basically פרנסה, parnassah, and then you turn to, you
know,
מקבץ נדחי עמו ישראל, mika-beitz nidchei amo Yisrael, אוהב צדקה ומשפט, ohev
tzedakah u'mishpat, למלשינים, lamalshinim, turn to national. All right, so it's an
interesting question whether the ברכת השנים, birkas hashanim, you know, is sort
of, it's communal, it's maybe it's not national in the same way
some of those others were. But anyway, but it could also be
very much seen as personal. So first of all, right, and I'm
just mentioning this because running to get to the תענית ציבור taanis
tzibur brain, if you're talking about the תענית ציבור taanis tzibur brain,
you would expect it to be in the ברכת השנים, birkas hashanim,
ברך עלינו את השנה הזאת. Bareich aleinu es hashana hazos. If it's
about that. And you'd certainly expect it to be in I would
say the more national and a little bit less of the personal
if it's because it's a תענית ציבור. taanis tzibur. And interestingly, we're
going to not going to find that. We're going to find it
here. But... In the case of the יחיד, Yachid, what it would
be doing here is I think that it goes to this issue
of what it's doing between גואל Goel and
רפואה Refuah is not exactly clear. But again, the question about maybe
it's connected to, I think the most logical sense is that it's
connected to this idea of גאולה, Geulah, again in that sort of
personal גאולה Geulah state and the sense of גאולה, Geulah, the idea
of redemption very much has a funny word because it very much
has I think a clear
religious connotation. The way like you can get healed, you can get
forgiven, other things like maybe, but גאולה Geulah has I think very
much this sense of God is גואל Goel you from your צרות
Tzarot and I do think, again, it's interesting about sort of seeing
the תענית Taanit and the idea of why at least a יחיד
Yachid would be the תענית Taanit connected to that sense of God's
redeeming us from our צרות. Tzarot. Yes.
I mean, also of course assuming the reason we're not getting rain
is because we've been doing bad things, we've been sinning or whatever,
we said סלח. Slach.
Yes, but
then it should have been after סלח. Slach. I understand, I understand,
but then it should have been after the סליחה. Slichah. So again,
and I've been saying that we have not been seeing סליחה Slichah
as an overly dominant theme here at all, right? I mean, it
does,
and again, I will, just to not to belabor the point but
just to mention, right? Look, listen to the themes mentioned in the
עננו. Aneinu. כי בצרה גדולה אנחנו, Ki Vetzarah Gedolah Anachnu, okay, that's
look how terrible we are. אל תפן לרשענו, Al Tefen Leresheinu, so
that is
the sort of the שכר ועונש Schar Va'onesh and the whatever, the
תשובה Tshuvah related aspect. אל תסתר פניך ממנו ואל תתעלם מתחינתנו היה
נא קרוב לשועתנו, Al Tasteir Panencha Mimenu Ve'al Titalam Mitchinatenu Heyeh Na
Karov Leshav'atenu, be close to us. It's all about being close to
us, right? There's an acknowledgment that maybe our bad deeds have separated
us, but it's all about being close to us. יהי נא חסדך
לנחמנו טרם נקרא אליך עננו, Yehi Na Chasdecha Lenachamenu Terem Nikra Elecha
Aneinu, it's about answering, right? עננו לא נענו, Aneinu Lo Na'anu, okay,
טרם יקרא ואני
אענה, Terem Yikra Ve'ani E'eneh, quoting a פסוק Pasuk that's all about
God's responsiveness, right? שאתה העונה בעת צרה פודה ומציל בכל עת, She'atah
Ha'oneh Be'eit Tzarah Podeh Umatzil Bechol Eis, right? So really I think
that the עננו, Aneinu, the theme of לא נענו Lo Na'anu and
being answered is the dominant and the כפרה, Kaparah, סליחה Slichah is
not, and it doesn't appear after סלח, Slach, it appears after גאולה.
Geulah. So I think that there is this sense about the need
for God to save us and God to help us, and it
is and that's where it's placed. Yes.
עננו Aneinu is plural. Yes, so but we're telling an individual.
Yeah, so, but everything is in the plural. Yeah. Yeah, but it's
a good point, like you could imagine a private one. Anyway, we're
going to get to the plural in a, to that idea in
a minute.
I think what's the simplest answer is the first three of those
ברכות, Brachot, right,
are about
relationship. גואל, Goel, the סליחה, Slichah, and the פונה בתשובה. Poneh Betshuvah.
Right, and then it goes into specific בקשות, Bakashot, right?
And so this is, עננו Aneinu is a relationship here.
Right, the only question I ask is how do you see גואל
Goel about the relationship?
ראה בעניינו, Re'eh Ve'onyeinu, you should, you should be cognizant of us
because you are the גואל ישראל. Goel Yisrael.
You see,
ראה בעניינו Re'eh Ve'onyeinu and then,
and then you get into much more
specific.
It's more about ראה Re'eh than it's interesting.
Okay, I'm not exactly sure again, you see our afflictions and you
save us from them
is more about the
relationship.
But alright. It doesn't have the same specificity.
Okay, that's true, it is, you're right, that is very general. And
I do think maybe the point you make about ראה בעניינו Re'eh
Ve'onyeinu because the whole issue about the תענית Taanit is עניינו Onyeinu
and again there's an interesting echo of עננו Aneinu and עניינו Onyeinu
and נענו. Na'anu. What? I'm versioning of תענית Taanit and ענייה Aniyah
and, anyway, but again, but notice this is the individual and the
point I also want to raise is who is this יחיד Yachid
so that is, that is being מתענה? Mit'aneh? Is it the individual
that wants to be פרום Frum and just wants to adopt the
תענית Taanit or wants to do an extra expression of religious practice,
or is it the יחידים Yechidim of the משנה Mishnah who are
being responsive to the lack of rain, that they're being responsive like
ahead of the curve? You know, is it still connected to the
rain or not is not clear. Alright, but anyway, let's take a
look at back to the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, problem is we're doing too much תורה, Torah, not enough דף
יומי. Daf Yomi. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, alright, so היכן אומרה בין גואל לרופא?
Heichan Omrah Bein Goel Leroifei? So מתקיף לה רב יצחק, Matkif Lah
Rav Yitzchak, so Rav Yitzchak challenges: וכי יחיד קובע ברכה לעצמו? Vachi
Yachid Koveia Brachah Le'atzmo?
You're an individual. That's not an allowance to change the liturgy. You
can insert certain things in certain places in the middle of a
ברכה, Brachah, but you can't change the liturgy as a יחיד. Yachid.
The liturgy is fixed, you know, only a
ציבור Tzibur could have a different type of a
תפילה. Tfilah. אלא אמר רב יצחק, Ela Amar Rav Yitzchak, rather says
Rav Yitzchak: בשומע תפילה. Beshomeia Tfilah. You just insert it in שומע
תפילה, Shomeia Tfilah, right,
which is what we, which is what we do. so
and we as get as we've talked about before by a private
שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei by a minor fast don't do it because
we're afraid we're not going to finish the fast, so it only
will appear מנחה Mincha and at מנחה Mincha here at שומע תפילה
Shomea Tefillah it says on fast days one has to add the
following: עננו השם עננו ביום צום תעניתנו Aneinu Hashem Aneinu beyom tzom
taaniteinu and it's exact same thing without the חתימה. Chatimah. Okay so
the גמרא Gemara doesn't know the difference between שחרית Shacharit and מנחה,
Mincha, but the גמרא Gemara is saying is so our resolution is
the יחיד Yachid does it does it in שומע תפילה, Shomea Tefillah,
the שליח ציבור Shliach Tzibur does it in as a separate ברכה
Berakhah בין גואל לרופא bein Goel l'Rofei like the גמרא Gemara is
saying and the other thing we add is that we wait until
מנחה Mincha for reasons we've discussed earlier. But that's what?
What? מנהג ספרדי? Minhag Sephardi?
Sephardic. So anyway but that's anyway but that's what we're dealing with.
Okay so back to the גמרא, Gemara, so which one is it?
Is it so our resolution is to split שליח ציבור Shliach Tzibur
and יחיד? Yachid? This is the גמרא's Gemara question. And you already
see the hint to that distinction in the in the גמרא Gemara
because the גמרא Gemara says a יחיד Yachid cannot make a new
ברכה Berakhah but the ציבור Tzibur theoretically could. So that is exactly
the way we wind up. אלא אמר רב יצחק בשומע תפילה. Ella
amar Rav Yitzhak b'shomea tefillah. וכן אמר רב ששת Vekhen amar Rav
Sheshet says רב ששת Rav Sheshet בשומע תפילה b'shomea tefillah in שומע
תפילה. Shomea Tefillah. מיתיבי Metivei I'll ask you on this says גמרא
Gemara אין בין יחיד וציבור אלא שזה מתפלל שמונה עשרה וזה מתפלל
תשע עשרה. ein bein yachid v'tzibur ella shezeh mitpallel shmoneh esrei v'zeh
mitpallel tisha esrei. The only difference between a יחיד Yachid and a
ציבור Tzibur by a תענית Taanit is that presumably the context is
this one says 18 and this one says 19. Now if you
have ever counted there are actually 19 ברכות Berakhot in our שמונה
עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, one was added later, but we're going to pretend
as if there's 18. You know, so it means that the ציבור
Tzibur adds an additional one. So מאי יחיד ומאי ציבור, mai yachid
u'mai tzibur, what's the יחיד Yachid and what's the ציבור? Tzibur? And
presumably the additional one that the ציבור Tzibur is adding is this
ברכה Berakhah of
עננו. Aneinu. So אילימא יחיד ממש וציבור שליח ציבור, ileima yachid mamash
v'tzibur shliach tzibur, if יחיד Yachid literal means in your private שמונה
עשרה Shmoneh Esrei and the ציבור Tzibur means the שליח ציבור Shliach
Tzibur which exactly fits our practice, so הני תשע עשרה? hani tisha
esrei? That's only 19. עשרים וארבע הוו! esrim v'arba havu! 24! Cause
we're going to find out in a later משנה Mishna that when
you got to the later fast days you would actually do a
whole, the ציבור Tzibur would דאוון, daven, not the יחידים yachidim but
the ציבור Tzibur would דאוון daven a special שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei
with six extra ברכות Berakhot inserted in the middle. So it can't
really mean a שליח ציבור Shliach Tzibur because that would be 24.
אלא לאו הכי קאמר: Ella lav hachi ka-amar: אין בין יחיד דקבל
עליו תענית יחיד ליחיד שקיבל עליו תענית ציבור. ein bein yachid dekabel
alav taanit yachid l'yachid shekibel alav taanit tzibur. The difference is it's
two cases of an individual a private individual fasting, in one case
he accepts to do a תענית יחיד Taanit Yachid meaning a lighter
version of the fast, only daytime, not all the extra עינויים, inuyim,
in one version he accepts a heavier version labeled תענית ציבור... Taanit
Tzibur... again it's interesting how that becomes a label for a way
of fasting and not just the reality of communal, starting the night
before, the extra עינויים. inuyim. So those differences in addition to the
obvious issues of starting it the night and the extra עינויים, inuyim,
the difference in terms of prayer is, אלא שזה מתפלל שמונה עשרה
וזה מתפלל תשע עשרה. ella shezeh mitpallel shmoneh esrei v'zeh mitpallel tisha
esrei. Okay. So with 18 and one 19. So therefore it can't
mean a real ציבור, Tzibur, it means an individual who's doing the
heavy fast and you see that an individual does a heavy fast
a תענית ציבור Taanit Tzibur it's 19 ברכות. Berakhot. So the גמרא
Gemara says שמע מינה shma mina we see from there יחיד קובע
ברכה לעצמו, yachid koveia berakhah l'atzmo, a יחיד Yachid can make his
own ברכה Berakhah if you're doing your heavy fast, starting the night
before, you would even do an עננו Aneinu in the שמונה עשרה
Shmoneh Esrei as a separate ברכה. Berakhah. So that's a proof. So
it's funny, a proof that starts by saying it's done by the
ציבור Tzibur becomes a proof that a יחיד Yachid can do it.
So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no, לעולם אימא לך שליח
ציבור, le-olam eima lakh shliach tzibur, it is a שליח ציבור, Shliach
Tzibur, the יחיד Yachid never does an extra ברכה Berakhah so to
speak stand-alone, it would only be in שומע תפילה. Shomea Tefillah. This
is the ציבור. Tzibur. Now if it's the ציבור Tzibur doing it
why is it 19 and not 24? דקקשיא לך de-kakashye lakh the
question you asked שליח ציבור עשרים וארבע מצלי shliach tzibur esrim v'arba
matzlei doesn't the שליח ציבור Shliach Tzibur do
24? Don't you do in חזרת הש"ץ Chazarat Hashatz on a fast
day 24? So the גמרא Gemara says בגימל תעניות ראשונות be-gimmel taaniyot
rishonot I'm sorry, we're talking about the first three fasts, the lighter
ones, right? That start even as a ציבור Tzibur fast start with
only in the day, not the night before, not the forbidden
מלאכות... melakhot... forbidden in תעניות taaniyot etc. דליכא עשרים וארבע deloka esrim
v'arba there's not 24. So basically when it's a communal fast, the
שליח ציבור Shliach Tzibur will do the ברכה Berakhah of עננו Aneinu
when in the lighter communal fasts and he'll do the 24 ברכות
Berakhot in the heavier communal fasts. A יחיד Yachid according to this
will always do it in שומע תפילה. Shomea Tefillah. Okay. Interestingly I
should say that the גמרא Gemara is interesting the גמרא's Gemara emphasis
on שליח ציבור, Shliach Tzibur, right? You could have said when the
community is having a ציבור תענית Tzibur Taanit then the יחידים yachidim
in their own שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei say it, but the גמרא
Gemara doesn't accept that as a possibility, so the גמרא Gemara presumably
assumes that in your private שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei whether you're doing
a תענית יחיד Taanit Yachid or תענית ציבור Taanit Tzibur we're not
going to allow you to change the liturgy. So you're only going
to add it in שומע תפילה, Shomea Tefillah, and that's what we
have in our own private שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, like even on
תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, we don't make it a separate ברכה, bracha,
we only add it in שומע תפילה. Shomea Tefillah. The only time
there's going to be a new ברכה bracha is in the חזרת
הש"ץ, Chazarat Hashatz, which really represents the entire community as a whole.
And for that חזרת הש"ץ, Chazarat Hashatz, for the earlier תעניות, Taniyot,
it's עננו, Aneinu, it's one extra ברכה, bracha, for the later תעניות,
Taniyot, it's six extra ברכות, brachot, you get to 24. Okay, so
that's our basic structure. So the גמרא Gemara says לאו, Lav, now
is this really true that you don't have 24 ברכות brachot in
the first sets of fasts? והא, אין בין תני, Ve-ha ein bein
tani? it says there's no difference. אין בין ג' ראשונות לג' אמצעיות,
Ein bein gimmel rishonot le-gimmel emtzaiyot, we have a ברייתא. baraita. There's
no difference between the first three and the middle
three, אלא שבאלו מותרין בעשיית מלאכה ובאלו אסורין בעשיית מלאכה, ella she-be-elu
mutarin ba-asiyat melacha u-ve-elu asurin ba-asiyat melacha, except that these are permissible
to do מלאכה melacha and these are forbidden to do מלאכה. melacha.
Now that's pretty funny because I can think of a lot of
other differences, right? Because you know, because they're all I didn't even
put some of them on the board. The question about does it
apply the day
before? רחיצה, rechitzah, סיכה, sichah, נעילת הסנדל, ne'ilat hasandal, תשמיש המיטה. tashmish
hamitah. Okay, so I don't get it exactly, but somehow we're meaning
I mean maybe like instead of the obvious stuff, okay, that's directly
about the fasting and the עינויים, inuyim, these are the differences. Okay,
but nothing else? So you see the תפילות tfillot are not different.
So the גמרא Gemara says הא לכ"ד זה וזה שוין. ha le-chaf
daled zeh ve-zeh shavin. When it comes to the 24 ברכות brachot
they're the same, so presumably you start the 24 even in the
first three fasts. So no, תנא ושייר. tana ve-shiyar. No,
he taught it and he left stuff off. It's an incomplete list,
an abbreviated list. מאי שייר דהאי שייר? Mai shiyar de-hai shiyar? What
did he leave off that he also left this, because you don't
leave off just one thing. If it's abbreviated, you know, if you're
going to if you're leaving one thing off, you might as well
list them all. So you can only leave off if you're leaving
off more than one. So the גמרא Gemara now of course, you
know, you could have said everything we just said. Night before, all
the extra עינויים, inuyim, somehow that's quite off the table. ותו, Ve-tu,
and in addition, הא אין בין תני. ha ein bein tani. It
says there's no difference. No difference sounds like literally no difference. אלא,
Ella, final, I'll give you another answer. תנא באיסורי קא מיירי בתפילות
לא קא מיירי. Tana be-issurei ka-mari bi-tfilot lo ka-mari. He's not dealing
with prayer, he's not dealing with liturgy, he's dealing with practices. Liturgy
is a different discussion. Okay, so you can't prove anything from there.
And even though it says there's no difference, it wasn't talking about
prayer, and we will still say that by prayer the כ"ד chaf
daled ברכות brachot only start
in the later fasts. ואיבעית אימא, Ve-ibaiy-teima, so and they don't start
in the first three. And if you want I could tell you,
באמצעיות נמי לא מטי כ"ד. be-emtzaiyot nami lo mati chaf daled. Since
it says there's no difference between the first three and the middle
three, maybe I'll concede the point. Maybe you're right. Maybe the 24
ברכות brachot don't start in the middle, maybe they only come at
the big seven at the end, right? Here's the difference what have
we said the difference is? The difference of this is obvious, right?
This becomes full with the extra things, no מלאכה, melacha, right? That's
obvious. What gets added here? I'm sorry, I'm sorry. The difference we
know between here and here is that this goes from like partials
to full. What's the difference we know between these and the last
seven? So the only thing we've mentioned so far is closing the
stores. Not too much of a difference, right? So the גמרא Gemara
says maybe the full blown here when it really gets to the
height of it, you only say the 24 ברכות brachot here. What
is the status of these middle for the 24 ברכות? brachot? That
is the question. Okay, this clearly not, this clearly yes, what's the
middle? So the גמרא Gemara says you know maybe you're right, maybe
at this stage it's still not fit to do the full 24,
maybe only for the last seven. Okay, and that would fit therefore
for the אין בין. ein bein. ואיבעית אימא באמצעיות נמי לא מטי
כ"ד. Ve-ibaiy-teima be-emtzaiyot nami lo mati chaf daled. הלא, Alo, do you
not do that? והתניא, Ve-hatanya, don't we teach in a ברייתא, baraita,
אין בין ג' שניות לשבע אחרונות? ein bein gimmel shniyot le-sheva achronot?
The only difference between the middle three and the last seven is
אלא שבאלו מתריעין ונועלין את החנויות. ella she-be-elu matriyin ve-noalin et hachanutiyot.
In the last seven you sound you do blasts, presumably שופר shofar
blasts, and you close the stores. And you close the stores, right?
הא לכל דבריהם זה וזה שוין, Ha le-chol divreihem zeh ve-zeh shavin,
they're the same. So presumably they're the same תפילות tfillot of 24.
וכי תימא הכא נמי תנא ושייר? Ve-chi teima hacha nami tana ve-shiyar?
Maybe it's an incomplete list? והא Veha, אין בין תני? ein bein
tani, Again it says no difference. No difference sounds like no difference.
So the גמרא Gemara says ותסברא? ve-tisburah? Does that really make sense?
אין בין דוקא? Ein bein davka? You think אין בין ein bein
is so precise? It literally means no difference? והשייר תיבה! Ve-hashiyar teiva!
It forgot the whole bringing the ark, the ark out to the
you know, the ארון aron out into the middle of the street.
So what we are going to find out is that in these
last seven, the גמרא Gemara is going to speak about a whole
procedure of 24 ברכות brachot for the שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, for
the 18 ברכות, brachot, the ארון aron is brought out into the
street, okay, we have a whole special liturgy, okay, ומתריעין, ve-matriyin, which
we haven't seen yet, which is presumably שופר shofar blast. So, so
the גמרא Gemara says yeah, but these are basically all the same.
which is a תפילה Tefillah related type of a thing. So if
you have a difference about this, and you have a difference about
the ארון, Aron, it makes sense that you also have a difference
that here's where you're saying, the only here do you start saying
the 24 ברכות. Brachot.
Okay, they added to the content of those additional.
Correct,
and we're getting to it. Not now, later פרק. Perek. So the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, דאשיבתא, Dashivta, so it didn't talk about the
ארון, Aron, so therefore it's an incomplete list and also another difference
is the 24 ברכות. Brachot. Says the גמרא, Gemara, אי משום תיבה,
Ei mishum teiva, if it's because of the ארון, Aron, so לאו
שיורא הוא, Lav shiyura hu, that's not a real thing that was
left off of the list. Why? מידי דצינעא קתני מידי דפרהסיא לא
קתני. Midi ditzina katani midi defarhesya lo katani. Things in private were
mentioned, things in public were not. Now it's pretty funny that it
calls a shofar blast something, the ארון Aron is in public, it's
out in the middle of the street. It's calling a shofar blast
private. So רש״י Rashi says it's private because it's indoors, it's in
the שול, Shul, it's not out in the middle of the street.
Okay, and I guess the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh is also indoors,
so it's pretty funny because all of those are real communal types
of experiences. It seems to be a pretty hair-splitting distinction. Anyway, but
ארון Aron used
to be closed behind something.
That's true. Okay. אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, מתניתין נמי דיקא.
Matnitin nami dika. Anyway, now what we're arguing is that the 24
only in the last seven, which fits to the idea of מטריעין
Matri'in and fits with the ארון. Aron. Those get a special whole
series of
תפילות. Tefillot. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, מתניתין נמי דיקא, Matnitin
nami dika, מה אלו יתירות על ראשונות, Mah elu yetirot al rishonot,
אלא שבמאלו מטריעין ונועלים את החנויות. Ela shebe-elu matri'in venoalin et hachanutiyot.
It says that the last fast, the seven, you do the blast
and you close the stores. אבל בכל דבריהם זה וזה שוין. Aval
bechol divreihem zeh vezeh shavin. We're going back to arguing that you
have again, the same argument just repeated except before it was the
ברייתא Braita and here it's the משנה. Mishnah. But it's the same
argument that the middle are being compared to the last, so presumably
if you do the 24 ברכות Brachot at the last, you do
them in the middle as well. וכי תימא הכא נמי תני ושיאר,
Vechi teima hacha nami tani veshayar, like rehashing the same thing. Again
here just playing on the text of the משנה. Mishnah. Maybe it's
an incomplete list. והא מה אלו קתני. Veha mah elu katani. It
says what you know what are them, it seems like it's a
full list, אלא שבמאלו, Ela shebe-elu, only these, like it seems like
it's a full list. And therefore again since it did not distinguish
with the ברכות, Brachot, it sounds like you do make the ברכה
Bracha in the middle. So the גמרא Gemara says ותסברא, Vetisbera, does
that make sense? מה אלו דוקא? Mah elu davka? ואשיבתא? Ve-ashivta? It's
not a full list, it didn't mention the bringing the ארון Aron
into the street. No, אי משום תיבה לאו שיורא הוא, Ei mishum
teiva lav shiyura hu, that's not, that's not really being left off
of the list משום דקחשיב ליה. Mishum dekachashiv lei. Now here's a
different answer. Here's where it shifts. Not because of פרהסיא Farhesya and
צינעא, Tzina, which was a weak answer, but משום דקחשיב ליה באידך
פירקא. Mishum dekachashiv lei be-idach pirka. The ארון Aron gets mentioned in
a later פרק, Perek, so it didn't have to appear in our
משנה Mishnah as one of the differences between the middle and the
last. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but if that explains something
that's not mentioned and not included in the, you know, here are
the differences, as long as it's mentioned later as a difference, so
השתא דאתית להכי, Hashta de-atit lehachi, now that you allow some differences
to be mentioned in a later פרק Perek and not excluded from
the equation made here, so עשרים וארבע נמי לאו שיורא הוא. Esrim
ve-arba nami lav shiyura hu. So the 24 also isn't something that's
left off of the
list, meaning isn't implicitly being equated, דקתני לה באידך פירקא, Dkatani lah
be-idach pirka, because a later פרק Perek mentions the 24 and it
mentions it by the last seven. So what we are basically saying
is that our משנה Mishnah mentions only the מטריעין. Matri'in. Okay. That
seems to indicate that they would be the same, right? This is
the middle. I know, I need more colors. Anyway, this is the
middle. This is the first, right?
And this is the last, okay, last seven.
Okay, so anyway, so our משנה Mishnah says the middle are like
the last, except for the מטריעין Matri'in and the stores. So that
suggests that the issue of the 24 ברכות Brachot are the same.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, that's only in the end and
then it, okay, that's only in the end, it's not here and
it's not a complete list. Okay, one of the explanations and so
then it yields that because there's this other difference ארון Aron that
also isn't mentioned in the equation. So the גמרא Gemara says well,
the reason ארון Aron isn't mentioned in the equation is not because
it's an incomplete list, it's because the ארון Aron is mentioned in
the later in another in the later פרק Perek that that's only
in the last seven days. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, but
you know what else is mentioned in the later פרק Perek that's
only on the last seven days? The 24 ברכות. Brachot. So both
of these are mentioned in a later פרק Perek that they are
in the last seven days and therefore they should not be assumed
to be included in the equation being made here. Okay, and in
the end the גמרא Gemara seems to be concluding that these 24
and work together, the מטריעין Matri'in and the ארון Aron and the
24, that all of that is only in the last seven days
and only there do you say the 24. So the גמרא Gemara
says
okay, מאי הוי עלה, Mai hava alah, what was of it? Yep,
so for all of this, so, אמר רב שמואל בר ססרטי וכן
אמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב: Amar Rav Shmuel bar Sasartai
v'chen amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav: בין גואל לרופא. Bein
goel l'rofe. So
abandoning for a moment the question of when do you say the
24, what do you do about the private, the individual making the
שמונה עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei? So he says בין גואל לרופא, Bein goel
l'rofe, a separate ברכה. bracha. ורב אשי אמר משמיה דרב ינאי בריה
דרב ישמעאל בשומע תפילה, V'Rav Ashi amar mishmei d'Rav Yannai brei d'Rav
Yishmael b'Shomea Tefillah, והלכתא בשומע תפילה. v'hilchasa b'Shomea Tefillah. The הלכה halacha
is you do it in שומע תפילה Shomea Tefillah and that's what
we do. Even in a תענית ציבור taanit tzibbur when we're doing
our private שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, we say עננו Anenu in שומע
תפילה. Shomea Tefillah. The גמרא's Gemara conclusion now is—this is getting way
too confusing and I need different and I need different things, but
anyway, the גמרא's Gemara conclusion is in your private שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh
Esrei, whether you are doing a תענית יחיד taanit yachid or a
תענית ציבור, taanit tzibbur, right, doesn't matter, in your private שמונה עשרה
Shemoneh Esrei you do it in שומע תפילה. Shomea Tefillah. In חזרת
הש"ץ, Chazarat Hashatz, okay, we won't talk about our historical fasts that's
coming up later, but you basically in the first three of them,
you do it in
עננו Anenu as a separate ברכה, bracha, you know, בין גואל לרופא.
bein goel l'rofe.
In
the last seven, you do 24 ברכות, brachos, here you're only doing
19 ברכות, brachos, okay, actually 20, but fine. And then the question
is the middle three. Okay, that's what we've been debating. Is the
middle three—how do you deal with the in-betweens? What's the issue with
the middle three? But the גמרא Gemara seems to be saying that
the middle three is only—seems to be coming to that conclusion, seems
to be leaving the 24 ברכות brachos for the end, which is
consistent with the end that you have the מתריעין, matri'in,
right, which are the שופר shofar blasts, and you have the תיבה
teva and you have a real expansion of the תפילה tefillah coming
at the end. Okay, let's—I said we're going to try to go
a little bit longer to try to catch up, so let's do
it. Okay, so תני חדא: Tani chada: עוברות ומניקות מתענות בראשונות ואין
מתענות באחרונות. Ubarot u'menikot mitanot b'rishonot v'ein mitanot b'acharonot. That pregnant women
and nursing women fast in the first days but not in the
last days. Okay, so which is bizarre because the first are usually
lighter, but here the idea is is that maybe it's getting to
be too much already, especially if the last is the last seven,
that's a lot. Okay, so only in the first days. ותניא אידך,
V'tanya idach, we have another ברייתא braisa that says: מתענות באחרונות ואין
מתענות בראשונות, Mitanot b'acharonot v'ein mitanot b'rishonot, only the last days, not
the first days. ותניא אידך: V'tanya idach: אין מתענות לא בראשונות ולא
באחרונות, Ein mitanot lo b'rishonot v'lo b'acharonot, not in the first and
not in the last. So they seem to all be contradicting, right?
One says only—so basically you
have one says A and not B, right, and the other says,
you know, it says B and not A, and the other says
not A and not B, right?
They all—the only fourth possibility would be to say both the first
and the last. But they all seem to be contradicting. So in
two words, the גמרא's Gemara got to make them all reconcile. Listen
to this. And without even changing a text, the גמרא Gemara says:
אמר רב אשי נקוט אמצעיתא בידך דמתרצן כולהו. Amar Rav Ashi nekut
amtzeita biyadech d'metartzan kulhu. Just grab the middle ones and everything fits.
What does he mean? He means that first and last are relative.
So what he is saying is is that if you have first,
middle, and last,
okay, so it says like this: You know which day—so you don't
fast here, okay, you don't fast here because that seven is too
much, you know, that's way too much for fast for the עובר
ubar and מניקות. menikot. You don't fast here because it's only the
beginning, it's lighter, it only starts in the daytime, it's not yet
serious enough to demand that the pregnant women, nursing women do it.
And the only time is here where it's heavy enough to be
fasting and not
too protracted that it would be unbearable. Now, how does that fit?
The one that says only the first and not the last, it's
talking about the first, it's talking about the weighty ones. This is
not the weighty ones, so only the first and not the last,
okay? This is first, that's last. The one that says only the
last and not the first is starting in the opposite direction. So
it's not the first but it is the last, right, because it's
the last following the first. It's later, אחרונות acharonot doesn't have to
mean the last, the later ones. And the one that says not
the first and not the last means literally the first and the
last. So you get the middle.
All right, so there you go. With that thing, you've solved all
three ברייתות. braisos.
Yes?
There's a נוסח nusach from the רמב"ם Rambam who says that pregnant
and nursing women only fast in the last.
Against this conclusion of the גמרא. Gemara. All right, I don't know
what to say about that.
Well, I want to say one possibility is that they take the
middle doesn't mean the middle fast, but the middle of the sequence.
Aha, interesting. Okay, I see that I'm losing my crowd here, so
I guess we won't be going for a longer thing. So let's
just—we'll end here and if the people could just wait one minute
and we will say the תפילה. tefillah. So let's just, we'll end
here and let's, but if people could just wait one minute and
we will say the תפילה Tefilla for the, for the captives and
the soldiers. Okay. Does
anybody have it? He's giving us a... okay. אבינו שבשמים Avinu Shebashamayim
צור ישראל וגואלו Tzur Yisrael Vegoalo ברך את מדינת ישראל Barech Et
Medinat Yisrael ראשית צמיחת גאולתנו Reshit Tzmichat Geulateinu הגן עליה באברת חסדך
Hagen Aleiha Be'evrat Chasdecha ופרוס עליה סוכת שלומך Ufros Aleiha Sukkat Shelomecha
ושלח אורך ואמתך לראשיה שריה ויועציה Ushlach Orecha Va'amitcha Lerashia Sareha Veyoatzeha
ותקנם בעצה טובה מלפניך Vetakenem Be'eitza Tova Milfanecha חזק את ידי מגיני
ארץ קדשנו Chazek Et Yedei Maginei Eretz Kodesheinu והנחילם אלהינו ישועה ועטרת
נצחון תעטרם Vehanchilem Eloheinu Yeshuah Veateret Nitzachon Teatrem ונתת שלום בארץ Venatata
Shalom Ba'aretz ושמחת עולם ליושביה Vesimchat Olam Leyoshveha ואת אחינו כל בית
ישראל Ve'et Acheinu Kol Beit Yisrael הפקודים בצרה ובשביה Hapekudim Betzara Uvashivyah
העומדים בין בים ובין ביבשה Haomdim Bein Bayam Uvein Bayabasha המקום ירחם
עליהם Hamakom Yerachem Aleihem ויוציאם מצרה לרווחה Veyotziem Mitzara Lirvacha ומאפלה לאורה
Umeafela Le'orah ומשעבוד לגאולה Umeshibud Ligeulah השתא בעגלא ובזמן קריב Hashta Ba'agala
Uvizman Kariv ונאמר אמן. Venomar Amen. Thank you all very much. I
hope you found something interesting. Thank you. Bye-bye. Bye-bye.